上帝也疯狂 II
The Gods Must Be Crazy II
这个看似乐园的地方 任何人来此...
Anyone else would die of thirst in a few days. In this arid desert...
都会因干渴而死 因为此地没有地表水
... that looks like a paradise, there's no surface water.
然而瘦长优雅的卡拉哈里土人...
But the slender, graceful Bushmen of the Kalahari...
却满足而自在地生活在其中
... live here contentedly and in complete harmony with their environment.
2万年来过著与世隔绝的生活...
They have lived undisturbed for 20,000 years because they are...
他们是世界上唯一不需要地表的水 而可以生活的人
... the only people in the world who know how to live without surface water.
当外地那些猎象牙的人来这里...
When ivory poachers in high-tech vehicles intrude into this thirst-land...
都得自己带著饮水来
... to hunt elephant, they have to drag reservoirs of water with them.
当水喝光时便只好开车 离开卡拉哈里沙漠
And when the water runs low they have to hightail it out of the Kalahari again.
土人在自己的世界中 隔绝地生活与嬉戏...
So the Bushmen work and play in peaceful isolation unaware...
对外界的汲汲与繁忙一无所知...
... of the crowded, hectic world outside their domain...
即使战争也只是在 卡拉哈里的边缘进行
... and even of the wars that are fought on the very fringes of the Kalahari.
有时奇哥谈他出外探险...
Sometimes Xixo tells about the time he looked for the end of the Earth...
遇见的一些奇人异事...
... and about the strange, heavy people he met...
但他很难描述外界的人
... but it's difficult to describe those who live outside the Kalahari.
最后只好说外界的人会变魔术...
He always ends by saying the heavy people know some magic...
让东西跑或飞，但他们不聪明...
... that can make things move and even fly, but they're not bright...
因为缺了那些东西之后 他们便无法生存
... because they can't survive without their magic contrivances.
他们喜欢在早上阅读新闻
In the mornings, they like to read the news.
他们知道土狼 有了新的女朋友...
They can read that the hyena has a new girlfriend...
印度豹的孩子不见了 而羚羊又开始向西迁移了
... the cheetah has lost a baby, and the oryx is migrating to the west.
大孩子教小孩子如何去解读 动物及邻居的闲话...
Older children teach younger ones how to read the gossip about the animals...
卡拉哈里发生的所有事情 都会印在沙上面
... because everything that happens in the Kalahari gets printed in the sand.
全都印在上面了 你委托人的专利权受到侵犯了
It's all printed out here. This is where they started infringing on the patent.
帮我找出来
Give it to me there.
我可以在法庭上提出来 再退回画面A
Now, that I can present in court. Go back to frame A.
看一下销售图
And give me sales.
嗨！安，这是杰夫！...
凯西，你去处理一下？ 拿掉吧
Cathy, will you take this? Take him off.
单位成本并列表
Now, cost per unit. And a printout on that.
杰夫先生说要去香港 处理接收的事
Mr. Geoffrey says he has to go to Hong Kong about the takeover.
- 好的，祝他"旅途愉快" - 他不能参加ECACL的会议
- Tell him, "Have a good flight." - He won't make the ECACI conference.
- 他不能这样对我 - 他说要你看一下报纸
- He can't do that to me. - He'd like you to read the paper.
说大多数是你研究的 你该得到这份荣幸的
You did the research, so you deserve the honor.
我要在星期三出庭
I have to take this case to court on Wednesday.
- 他说周三前会回来的 - 老天！
- Says you'll be back before Wednesday. - Oh, boy.
当天早上卡比由丛林回来...
That morning, Xabe came with the news that...
说有些动物开始向北迁移
... the animals are moving towards the marula groves in the north.
他对爸爸说："这些野果子 已成熟了，我们去摘吧"
He shouted, "The marulas are ripe. Let's go collect some."
奇沙和奇尔跑过来说： "我们也可以去吗？"
Xisa and little Xiri ran up and said, "Can we come too?"
奇哥说："我看看你够不够大 如果你比我的弓高...
Xixo said, "Let's see if you're big enough. If you're taller than my bow...
土狼就会怕你而远离你 如果你不够高，它就会咬你"
... the hyena will be afraid and stay away. If you're shorter, he'll take you."
但奇尔说： "求你也让我去吧！"
But Xiri said, "Please let me come too."
奇沙说： "我保证一定好好看著他"
And Xisa said, "I promise I'll always stay close to him."
- 今年在哪开会？ - 在艾尔卡卡克拉
- Where is the conference this year? - In Okakarara.
- 是尼布拉斯加吗？ - 不是，是非洲
- Where's that, Nebraska? - No, Africa.
老天！
Oh, boy.
他们摘了好多野果子回来 回家途中看到...
They gathered a lot of marulas and on the way home they found...
一只受伤的大象足迹
... the spoor of a wounded elephant.
奇哥说："这只大象太衰弱了 它会死掉"
Xixo said, "This elephant is very weak. It's going to die."
他对奇沙说："你和奇尔回家
He said to Xisa, "You and Xiri can go on home.
告诉你妈我找到大象后就回家"
Tell your mother we will come when we've found the sick elephant."
地上有个形状很奇怪又美丽
There was a very strange and beautiful pattern on the ground.
奇沙看不懂 她一辈子也没看过这种东西
Xisa couldn't read it. She'd never seen anything like it in her life.
还有一个，跟刚才的一样美
There was another as beautiful as the first.
她想不出是什么东西会有 这种持续的印子
She wondered how anything could make such a long, unbroken track.
她跟著印子走 看见一个很奇怪的东西
She followed the track and saw a very strange-looking thing.
她说： "那个东西一直在转...
She said, "This thing went round and round...
所以才 造成了这么长的图案"
... and that's how it made such a long pattern without footprints."
奇尔看到一颗露珠正在凝聚...
Xiri saw a beautiful dewdrop grow, and when it dropped...
掉了一颗，另一颗又快出现了
... another one began to grow in its place.
他们知道上帝在晚上把 露珠放在树上
They knew the gods put dewdrops on plants in the night.
但现在却在白天看到露珠
But here they could see a dewdrop form in broad daylight.
奇沙说： "水一定是这个东西做的"
Xisa said, "I think this thing is making the water."
奇尔这辈子没看过这么多水
Xiri had never seen so much water in his life.
他不知道世界上居然有这么多水
He didn't know there was so much water in the whole world.
终于找到大象了 他们看到让大象死的小伤口
They found the elephant and saw the tiny wounds that had made it die.
这些痕迹让奇哥知道 是外界的人做的...
The tracks told Xixo the heavy people had been there...
却纳闷他们为何把没用的象牙 拿走却把珍贵的肉留下任其腐烂
... but wondered why they took the useless tusks and left the meat to rot.
他说："他们真奇怪"
He said, "The heavy people are strange."
波说："我去叫自己家人来吃肉
Bo said, "I'll call Xabo's family to help us eat it.
即使跑一天一夜 也可在明天找到他们"
If I run all day and night I can find them by tomorrow."
奇哥说："我们去叫自己的家人来"
Xixo said, "We'll go call our family."
有好多象牙，上帝需要比人的寿命 还长的时间才能...
There were many tusks. It takes the gods more than a man's lifetime...
让成象长好，看到这么多 象死掉，让他们害怕无比
... to make a full-grown elephant, and it horrified them to see so many had died.
奇哥和奇比找到奇沙和奇尔 脚印中断的地方
Xixo and Xabe found the place where Xisa and Xiri's tracks suddenly stopped.
奇哥说："你看，奇沙和 奇尔爬上去被带走了"
Xixo said, "Xisa climbed onto the thing. Xiri went up too, and it took them away."
他说："回去告诉家人快去吃死象"
He said, "Tell our family they must start eating the dead elephant.
我去找奇沙和奇尔
I'll fetch Xisa and Xiri."
ECACL会议
抱歉临时通知 不过，很荣幸有你们光临
Sorry about the short notice, but we're honored to have you.
谢谢你 我也很想去狩猎之旅
Thank you. I would've liked the safari tour...
- 可是我要准备报告 - 你当真没事？
...but I have to prepare my presentation. - You'll be all right?
- 没事，谢谢你 - 好，那就不打扰了
- I'll be fine, thank you. - Good. I'll leave you to it.
- 史帝芬现在在哪儿？ - 我多少有点概念
- You know where Stephen's working? - I think I've got a rough idea.
- 你得去找一番了 - 对
- You may have to search around a bit. - Right.
- 杰克 - 是的
- And Jack? - Yeah?
跟史帝芬说我们会把 其他东西送去给他
Tell Stephen we'll send the rest of the stuff out to him later.
像你这么好的小姐 怎么会来这里的？
What's a nice girl like you doing in a place like this?
- 老天 - 你不吃这套？
- Oh, boy. - You don't buy it.
好，我再试一次
Okay, I'll try again.
- 嗨，想不想陪我去飞行？ - 我为了准备这个才拒绝去狩猎的
- Hi. Like to come fly with me? - I have to work. That's why no safari trip.
这一趟要三小时 我半小时内就可以让你看完非洲
Trip's three hours. I could show you Africa in half an hour.
我三点半要报告的
I have to present this at 3:30.
研讨会主讲：安泰勒博士
- 只要半小时？ - 是的，博士
- Only half an hour? - Yes, doctor.
- 你是医学博士？ - 不是，公司法
- So, what are you, a doctor of medicine? - No, corporate law.
- 好小的飞机啊 - 还有更小的，可惜找不到
- What a tiny plane. - We got a smaller one but can't find it.
- 可以飞吗？ - 进去吧！
- Can it fly? - In you go.
- 那是什么？ - 水牛啊
- What are those? - Buffalo.
看，手可以放掉，自动在飞 最安全的飞机
Look, no hands. Flies by itself. Safest plane in the world.
- 咖啡 - 早安，老板
- Coffee. - Morning, boss.
- 才开80哩 - 对呀，我睡了一会
- You only done 80 miles. - Yeah, I slept a little bit.
- 你停过 - 我太累了，所以停了一会....
- You stopped. - I was bushed. So I pulled up and...
- 你睡了四个多小时 - 真的累坏了
- You slept more than four hours. - I was real pooped.
- 我早说过快迟到了 - 我真的好累，老板
- I told you we're late. - I was really pooped, boss.
- 过去点 - 没关系，精神来了
- Move over. - It's okay, boss. I'm fresh now.
哎呀，老板
Jeez, boss.
懒骨头
Lazy bastard.
- 回去睡吧 - 我现在清醒的很呢
- Get back to sleep. - I'm wide-awake now.
- 睡吧 - 是的，老板
- Sleep. - Yes, boss.
我马上回来
I'll be right back.
- 嗨！史帝芬 - 嗨！谢谢！
- Hi, Stephen. - Hi. Thanks.
你飞的很好 只是云层会越来越多
You're cutting it fine. There's a hell of a cumulus building up.
万一被碰上 你就会从2万英尺摔下来
One of those thermals grabs you, it's gonna whip you right to 20,000 feet.
- 待会见 - 史帝芬，杰克到了没？完毕
- See you later. - Stephen, is Geoff there yet? Over.
嗨！巴伯，他来了，完毕
Hi, Bob. Yes, he's here. Over.
可以跟他飞回去吗？
Can you fly back in with him?
我们发现一只重病的长颈鹿 请你提供意见，完毕
We found a sick baby giraffe. We need your advice. Over.
好的，完毕
Okay. Out.
- 你不该带情人来的 - 她不是情人
- You can't cart your floozies around. - She's not a floozy.
- 嗨！ - 早安！
- Hi. - Morning.
你是在这附近工作吗？
Do you do some kind of work around here?
史帝芬，快回答，完毕
Hello, Stephen. Come in. Over.
史帝芬，你在吗？完毕
Stephen, are you there? Over.
- 史帝芬，快回答，完毕 - 巴伯，我是杰克，完毕
- Stephen, come in. Over. - Hi, Bob. This is Jack. Over.
杰克，先别起飞 暴风以快速朝北前进，完毕
Jack, don't take off yet. There's a freak storm moving in very fast. Over.
- 巴伯，他们刚走，完毕 - 他们？还有别人跟他一起？完毕
- Bob, they've just taken off. Over. - They? Someone is with him? Over.
- 是的，完毕 - 是谁？完毕
- Yes. Over. - Who? Over.
- 一位小姐，完毕 - 和你一起的？完毕
- There was this young lady. Over. - Was she with you? Over.
- 差不多，完毕 - 你麻烦大了，完毕
- Sort of. Over. - Boy, you're in trouble. Over.
完毕
Over.
奇哥的朋友瓦卡站在那看 外人留下的印子
Xixo's old friend Waka was looking at the tracks the heavy people made.
奇哥向他问好说自己的孩子 在造成印子的东西上面
Xixo greeted him and said his children were in the thing that made the tracks.
瓦卡也向他问好 说："我陪你去找孩子"
Waka greeted him back and said, "I'll come with you to find your children."
但奇哥说："那儿有只死大象
But Xixo said, "There's a dead elephant back there.
让你的家人帮我家人去吃象肉吧"
Go with your family to help my family eat it."
高度24987英英尺
高度24991英英尺
高度25000英英尺
停了
They stopped.
- 你座位底下有威士忌 - 我没事
- There's whiskey under your seat. - I'm okay.
- 拿给我喝 - 你要喝酒？
- Give it to me. - You gonna start drinking?
给我！
Give me.
这玩意喝了酒能飞？
Can this thing fly on Scotch?
乔治
George.
老板？
Boss?
你来接替
Take over.
奇沙说："这东西累了以后就要休息
Xisa said, "When this thing gets tired it will rest.
我们可以跟著印子回家"
Then we can follow the tracks back home."
威士忌没有了
Running out of Scotch.
这有用吗？
This any good?
我们在倒飞
We're flying backwards.
我三点半要做报告
I have to read my paper at 3:30.
我怎么回去？ 得找路搭便车
How do I get back? We have to find a road so I can hitch a ride.
朝哪走最接近公路？
So which way to the nearest road?
- 这里是野蛮区 - 我看得出来
- This is baobab country. - It can speak.
- 距离机场至少3百哩 - 老天！
- We're at least 300 miles from base. - Oh, boy.
可能不止
Maybe more.
- 抱歉 - 随时候教
- I'm sorry. - Any time.
- 我得去打个电话 - 我连在哪儿都不知道
- I have to get to a phone. - I don't even know what country we're in.
嘿！
Hey!
- 什么！ - 他们不怕我
- What? - They're not scared of me.
- 如何？ - 他们不知道人这种东西
- So? - They don't know about people.
- 我们在卡拉哈里内部 - 他们会找到我们吗？
- We're in the deep Kalahari. - Will they find us?
- 迟早的事 - 究竟要多久？
- Eventually. - How long is eventually?
也许是一天，也许是一星期
Maybe a day, maybe a week.
一星期？我周三要回纽约
I have to be back in New York on Wednesday.
- 你从纽约来？ - 你要我在这过一星期？
- You're from New York? - I have to survive here for a week?
能在纽约活在这就死不了
Anyone who can survive in New York can survive here.
- 我们会饿死 - 这儿有吃不完的食物
- We'll starve to death. - There's enough food around here.
水才是问题 我们只有那些啤酒
Our problem will be water. All we have is that six-pack up there.
他们很渴 但知道那儿有水
They were getting thirsty, but they knew where there was plenty of water.
她说："我太重了拉不上来
She said, "No, I'm too heavy to pull up.
你下来推我好了 然后我再拉你上来"
Come down here so you can push me up. Then I can pull you up."
奇尔一辈子没下过水...
Xiri had never been in water in his life...
但很快就习惯而喜欢上
... but soon got used to it and quite enjoyed it.
是水吗？
Is that water?
- 汽油，燃料 - 怎么样？
- Petrol. Gas. - So?
如果能把飞机弄下来 就可以开了
If I can get this down, we can fly out.
今天？
Today?
我得拆开拿下来再装配好
I have to take it apart, bring it down, assemble it again.
- 终于！ - 可能明天会好或后天
- Eventually. - Maybe by tomorrow, the next day.
是狮子吗？
Was that a lion?
- 我听到了 - 绳子放下，我要上去
- I can hear them. - Let down the rope. I want to get up.
- 它们不会来的 - 你没关系
- They won't bother us. - You're okay.
- 我在下面呀 - 它们不会过来的
- They're bothering me down here. - They're not coming this way.
万一呢？
What about eventually?
你不惹它们，它们就不惹你
Don't bother them, they won't bother you.
- 如果它们饿了呢？ - 它们离这里很远
- And if they're hungry? - They're far from here.
下面全是野兽
It's swarming with wild animals here.
别惹它们就不会有事
Don't bother them, they won't bother you.
我没惹它们呀
I'm not bothering them.
这一只在垂涎我
This one is drooling at me.
- 是土狼，本来就流口水 - 所以呢？
- It's a hyena. They're always drooling. - So?
别管它，别对它笑 它看见你的牙齿...
Ignore him. Don't smile at him. He sees your teeth...
- 会认为你在威胁它 - 让我上去
...he might think you're threatening him. - Let me get up.
- 你很享受呀 - 对
- You're enjoying this. - Yeah.
- 为什么你不放轻松也享受一下？ - 享受？
- Why don't you relax and enjoy it too? - Enjoy?
- 这么多野兽，没食物也没水 - 也没房间服务
- Wild animals, no food, no water. - No room service.
对，也没卫浴 我现在需要卫浴
Yeah, no plumbing. What I need is plumbing. Now.
- 到树丛后面 - 一个人？狮子在那边呀
- Go behind that thicket. - Alone? The lions are that way.
- 它们在很远，如果你不惹- - - 它们就没事，我知道了
- They're very far. If you don't bother... - They won't bother me. I know, I know.
- 怎么下去啊？ - 怎么上去的？
- How do I get down? - How'd you get up there?
- 狮子吼的 - 不是狮子
- The lion was roaring. - Wasn't a lion.
是土狼在叫
It was a hyena sounding off.
对
Right.
等一下，转过去
Now, just a minute. Turn your back.
- 拉起来 - 不行，有阻力
- Pull me up. - I can't. Friction.
放我下来
Then let me down.
- 停 - 你要我怎么做？
- Stop. - What do you want me to do?
- 别看我 - 我没看你，你要我怎么做？
- Don't look at me. - I'm not. What do you want me to do?
放下来
Let me down.
什么好笑的？
What's so funny?
好吧，我不打扰你 你也别打扰我
Okay, I won't bother you, see? So don't you bother me.
- 小心！ - 快走开
- Watch it! - Go away!
快跑，快跑... 爬到树上
Run, run, run, run, run, run. Get up a tree!
你没事吧？
You okay?
- 你说只要不惹它们.... - 有小犀牛在呀
- You said if I didn't bother them... - I see there's a baby rhino.
母牛以为你在骚扰它
Maybe the mother thought you were molesting it.
我只跟它说话而已 没有对它微笑
I only talked to it. I didn't even smile at it.
- 它们会走开 - 你不飞...
- They're going away. - I'm not coming down...
- 我出去之前我不下来 - 上面没卫浴呀
...before you can fly me out of here. - There's no plumbing up there.
- 你渴了？ - 对！
- You thirsty? - Yes.
- 来，半罐啤酒给你 - 太好了
- Right, you can have half a beer. - Great.
- 先别打开 - 抱歉，噢，老天！
- Don't open it yet. - Sorry. Oh, my goodness.
抱歉，我哪做错了？
Sorry. What did I do wrong?
是温的，喝了吧
Well, it's warm. Drink it now.
好，时间不早了
Right. It's getting late.
趁天黑前找食物吧 我看见鸵鸟巢
We have to find food before it gets dark. I saw an ostrich nest.
- 会咬人吗？ - 不会，它们会踢人，但不太聪明
- Do they bite? - No, they kick. But they aren't bright.
只要躺著，它就看不见了 那只是公的，它在监视蛋
You lie down flat, he can't see you. That's the male. He guards the eggs.
- 如果你引开公鸵鸟.... - 如何引开公鸵鸟？
- But if you can distract him... - How do I distract a male ostrich?
躺下
Lie down flat!
奇哥以为自己看见了孩子的脚印...
Xixo thought he saw his children's footprints...
但其实是一只猩猩的
... but it was only a baboon that had walked past.
- 怎么回事？ - 没事！蛋拿到了
- So, what went wrong? - Nothing. We got the egg.
这是标准做法？
You mean that was standard procedure?
有火吗？
Got a match?
又回来了，抱歉
The thing came back. I'm sorry.
- 有火吗？ - 有打火机
- You got a match? - I got a lighter.
大班呼叫蓝吉 大班呼叫蓝吉，听到没有？
Big Ben calling Ramjee. Big Ben calling Ramjee. Do you read me?
蓝吉回答，大班呼叫
Ramjee, come in. Big Ben calling.
- 快回答，蓝吉，还是收不到 - 或许还没到
- Come in, Ramjee. Still out of range. - Maybe they're not there yet.
他说九号会面的 是昨天
He said he'd meet us on the ninth. That's yesterday.
抱歉，老板
Sorry, boss.
...一万个人要参加开幕典礼 虽然有九架直升机...
- 10,000 people will attend the opening. Although nine helicopters...
还有四架飞机一起搜寻 但没有马歇尔和泰勒博士的行踪
... and four planes are taking part, no sign of Dr. Marshall and Dr. Taylor.
- 是说我们？ - 大概是
- Was that us? - I suppose so.
- 什么博士？ - 动物学
- Doctor of what? - Zoology.
- 你呢？ - 法律学
- You? - Law.
- 我们得小心点 - 土狼？
- We have to watch that guy. - Hyena?
对，它是个懦夫，只要你比它 高大，它就不敢近身
He's a coward. If you're taller than him, he'll keep his distance.
如果你躺下，它就会过来 咬烂你的脸和腿
But if you lie down he'll sneak up and take a chunk out of your leg.
你来当第一班 月亮到那时再叫我...
Take first watch. Call me when the moon gets there...
我就守到那 然后你就可以守到天亮
...I'll take it to there, then you take it to first light.
下来了
Coming down.
- 我好了 - 为了什么？
- I'm ready. - For what?
你只跳25公分 正常的程序呢？
You only jumped 25 centimeters. What happened to standard procedure?
下一次吧！
Maybe next time.
- 我们到哪起飞？ - 3哩外有一块平地
- Where we gonna take off from? - There's a saltpan three miles from here.
那是几条街远？
How many blocks is that?
让太阳保持在你右肩 离矮树枝远一点
Keep the sun over your right shoulder. Stay clear of low branches.
- 什么？ - 那只臭犀牛
- What? - It's that damn rhino.
是公的，不会伤人 干嘛老往树上爬呢？
It's a male. It's harmless. Why are you always climbing up trees?
我不是动物学博士 我要如何分辨出公母来？
I'm not a doctor of zoology. How do I know about males and females?
差点把机鼻撞坏
Damn near wrecked the nose wheel.
推我一把
Give me slack.
- 你只跳124公分 - 这些东西很危险的
- You only jumped 124 centimeters. - These things are dangerous.
它很小
It's very small.
- 被它咬中绝不放口的 - 满可爱的
- When it grabs hold it never lets go. - Kind of cute.
不要！
Hey. No!
- 现在轮胎破了 - 这个怎么处理？
- Now we've got a flat. - What do I do with this?
- 为何不丢了它？ - 它还会跑回来的
- Why don't you throw it away? - It'll just come right back.
可以换轮胎吗？
Can you change the tire?
- 可以帮我脱靴子吗？ - 为什么？
- Can you undo my boot? - Why?
是踢它的那只 给它的话，它就可以报仇了
It's the one that stepped on him. If I give it to him, he can have his revenge.
- 汽油够我们回去吗？ - 足够起飞的
- Is there enough gas to take us back? - If we get it off the ground.
- 不管用 - 你会修吗？
- No, it won't work. - Can't you fix it?
没有唧筒
No pump.
你想当轮子 你疯了！
You wanna be the wheel. You're crazy.
你看见棍子了？ 我叫开始，你就带过来
You see that stick? When I shout, bring it this way.
- 我不会开飞机啊 - 我会把你那边举高，再恢复平衡
- I can't fly. - It'll lift your side, then center up.
我再叫，你就拉回来
When I shout again, pull back.
拉回来，中间，回头
Bring it over, center, pull back.
- 然后呢？ - 由我来接手
- Then what? - I'll take over.
我连半自动的都不会开 你想害死我们两个？
But I can't even drive a manual. Do you wanna kill us both?
你疯了，我不会开飞机 听到没有？
You're nuts. I can't fly. Do you hear me?
- 我不会开飞机呀 - 节流阀
- I can't fly a plane. - Throttles.
- 什么？ - 亮的那个，往前推一下
- What? - Shiny ones, push them forward.
我们出发吧
Here we go.
- 来吧，拉起来，再中间 - 我说过我不会开飞机的
- Come on. Stick it back. Center up. - I told you I can't fly.
就现在，往回拉
Right now, pull back.
- 你说往回拉 - 不是全力
- You said pull back. - Not way back.
- 拉它、拉它、拉它 - 你可不可以拿定主意？
- Pull it, pull it, pull it. - Will you make up your mind?
- 把它放下来、把它放下来 - 什么？
- Bring her down, bring her down. - What?
- 该往那边开的 - 你说要接手的
- We go that way. - You said you were gonna take over.
- 你该往那边开的，狗屎！ - 狗屎！
- You should have gone that way. Shit. - Shit.
女人什么都干不成 她终于飞了
Trust a woman to do anything, and she buggers it up.
她越来越会飞了
So she buggered it up.
开 关
低下头看看"开/关"字样 关掉就可以滑翔了
Look down and read. It says, "onloff." Switch it off, then glide.
降落伞
我说过不会飞的
I told you I can't fly.
它写著："降落伞"很清楚
It says, "Ballistic parachute." Clearly.
你看清楚，按下按钮时 就没事了
Read it. Press the button. You'll be okay.
我说过连半自动的都不会
I told you I can't even drive a manual.
很简单，拉起来，放中间 拉回来，就行了
It's easy. Bring it over, center it up, pull back. Get it right!
我示范的很明白，我叫你 "拉过来"不是"拉过来！"
I showed you so nicely. I said, "Bring it over." Not, "Bring it over!"
你会摔断脖子的
You'll break your neck.
你没说明清楚 我可能会弄断我的脖子
You don't explain properly. I could have broken my neck.
我只有一只靴子怎么找你呀？
How am I going to find you with only one boot?
先找靴子吧
Better find my boot.
走开！
Shoo. Go away.
狗屎！
Shit.
等等！
Wait!
嗨，你的单车可以卖我吗？
Hi. Do you want to sell me your bike?
你看，我给你钱
Look. I'll give you money.
我给你钱，你给我单车
I give you money, you give me the bike.
我要去那边，那有个人 我付你钱，你带我过去
I have to go that way. There's a man. I'll pay you, you take me that way.
拿去！
Here.
拜托，我坚持 好吧，到了再给你，坐这？
Please, I insist. Okay. Pay you when we get there. There?
我们试点别的吧？
Well, why don't we try something else?
好的
Yeah, sure.
好
All right.
想的妙！
Good thinking.
你打算咬一辈子？
Are you gonna hang in there forever?
来吧，午餐，尝尝看
There. Lunch. Go on, try it.
好，尝这个
Okay, try that.
我很抱歉，这个拿去
Look, I'm really sorry. Please, take this.
不，拿去吧
No, come on.
再见
Bye.
谢谢，再见 得去找人了
Well, thanks. Bye. Gotta find somebody.
你说你累了
You said you were tired.
回家吧！
Hey, go home.
回你家
Go back to your family.
快走呀，快走！
Go on, get.
快走，走...
Get. Shoo. Go.
英语？
English?
好吧
Okay.
起来！
Get up.
- 走 - 往哪走？
- Move. - Which way?
我的吉普车
To my jeep.
停！你要去哪里？
Stop. Where are you going?
你的吉普车在哪里？
Where is your jeep?
我要去你的吉普车
We go to your jeep.
停！
Stop.
- 前进 - 往哪去？
- March. - Which way?
你知道罗盘后面为何有镜子吗？
Know why a compass is a mirror on back?
- 为什么？ - 可以看到谁迷路
- Why? - So you can see who's lost.
好，走西北方向 那边，前进
Okay. We go northwest. That way. March.
你究竟飞了多远？
How far did you fly, for Pete's sake?
我怎么找你呀？
How am I going to find you?
该死
Damn.
嘿！
Hey.
嘿！你，走开，别乱动
Hey, you, get away. Leave it alone.
快滚开！
Get out of here.
罐子还我，混蛋
Give me back my can. Scumbag.
你这只土匪
You mugger.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你别过来
You keep away.
别动
Stay there.
看到没有，你敢过来....
See these? You dare...
别动歪脑筋
Don't even think about it.
你会后悔的
You'll be sorry.
走开！
Go away.
好吧，这是你最后一次喝了
Okay. You can have this one and no more.
别碰罐子，听见没？
Leave the can. Do you hear me?
别碰罐子，走开！
Leave my can alone and go away.
别带朋友来
No, don't bring a friend.
我不会替你这些亲朋好友浇水的- -
I'm not gonna water you, your friends and your relatives, and I'm not...
- 日内瓦会议摘要 - 算了吧！
- Excerpts from the Geneva Convention. - Forget it.
上面提到对待战俘的方法
How a prisoner of war ought to be treated.
"战犯不得受到非人道的待遇
"No prisoner shall be subjected to inhumane treatment.
- 不得使用暴行" - 停！
- No outrage shall be committed." - Stop.
- 你可以休息3分钟了 - 你怎么这么急？
- You can rest for three minutes. - What's your hurry?
不关你的事
None of your business.
3分钟
Three minutes.
我累死了
I'm pooped, man.
别跑啊，回来！我要把你 呈报到日内瓦会议
Don't do that. Come back. I'm going to report you to the Geneva Convention!
回来，你是人犯，回来
Come back. You're my prisoner. Come back!
回到我这儿来，你是我的人犯
Come out of there and be my prisoner!
- 你不能这么做！ - 前进
- You mustn't do that! - March.
如果你聪明，怎么会连 身处在什么国家都不知道？
If you're so smart, how come you don't even know what country you're in?
他们朝哪走了呢？
So which way did they go?
看来只好等他们回来了
I'll just have to wait till they come back.
奇哥看见外人穿怪衣服...
Xixo saw a heavy person dressed in funny clothes...
自言自语 她看来像女人，但是男人声
... talking to herself. She looked like a woman, but had a man's voice.
嘿
Hey.
这是你问好的方式 我们是这种做法
It's your way of greeting. We do it this way.
抱歉
Sorry.
好吧，照你的方式做
Okay. I'll do it your way.
哈啰，很高兴认识你
Hello. I'm very glad to meet you.
他说："你的家人在哪？"
He said, "Where is your family?"
他看了一下印子说 "你一个人怎么来的呢？
He looked at her tracks and said, "How did you get here?
我得找我的孩子 但有两个外人在那玩游戏
I have to find my children, but two people are playing some game.
刚才听见他们朝这儿来了
They went that way. I hear them.
- 或许他们会让你一起玩" - 要我一起去？
- Perhaps they'll let you play." - You want me to go?
他带她去两个外人的所在
He showed her the tracks where he met the two heavy men.
说这是他们回头的地方
He said, "This is where they turned back.
这个人很生气，因为累的那个人 抢了他的棍子
This one was angry because the tired one grabbed the stick.
然后他得逃跑，真好笑
And then he had to run. It was very funny."
她当然听不懂了，她也很文盲
She couldn't understand. She was also quite illiterate.
她看不懂符号和印子
She couldn't read the signs and tracks at all.
我们等巴士？
We're waiting for a bus?
真想不到呀
Well, what do you know.
走，滚，我不想看到你 停！
Go away. Bugger off. I don't want to see you. Stop!
你是谁？
Who are you?
奇哥不明白那些疯子玩什么把戏
Xixo couldn't understand what they were playing.
这玩意会穿透的
This thing penetrates.
你不会伤害女人吧？
You wouldn't shoot a lady.
他说："我得去找孩子"
He said, "I have to find my children."
他记得那些人态度很差 所以也没说再见
The men had bad manners, so he didn't say goodbye.
我不想涉及你们的争端 我是美国人
I don't want to be involved. I'm American.
好吧！
Okay.
嘿，不能丢下我不管 你要我死吗？
Hey, you can't leave me here. You want me to die?
离我远点
Get away from me.
走开
Get away.
再一次？
Try again, huh?
这不公平，你们不能利用我
It's not fair. You can't both use me.
放开我！放开我！放开我！
Let me go! Let me go. Let me go!
好了，丢掉
Okay, drop it.
- 丢掉 - 丢掉
- Drop it. - Yes, drop it.
- 丢掉 - 丢掉，丢掉，丢掉！
- Now, drop it. - Yes, drop it, drop it, drop it!
可以谈判吗？
Can't we negotiate?
我要回家，如果明天不到比耶 就赶不上回古巴的飞机了
I wanna go home. If I don't get back to Biera, I'll miss my plane to Cuba.
- 不然又要在非洲过6个月 - 我要带你回基地
- I'll spend another six months here. - I've got to take you to my base!
- 我得赶在周三回纽约 - 坐下来，离那个古巴佬远点
- I must be in New York on Wednesday. - Sit down. And stay clear of the Cuban.
我要离你们两个远点
I'll stay clear of goddamn both of you.
我讨厌被人利用当人质
I resent being used as a hostage object.
我得在周三回纽约
Gotta be in New York on Wednesday.
你该留在这 我没叫你出来的
You should have stayed there. I didn't ask you to come out here.
为了找你，腿都快断了
I have to walk my arse off to find you.
很好
Well, good.
什么好笑的？
What's so funny?
打开
Switch it on.
大班呼叫蓝吉 大班呼叫蓝吉
Big Ben calling Ramjee. Big Ben calling Ramjee.
- 你干什么？ - 我干什么？老板
- What are you doing? - What am I doing?
看看太阳，方向走错了
Look at the sun. You're going the wrong way.
老板，我照罗盘开的呀
Boss, I'm driving on the compass.
这玩意是钢做的 你却留在那
This thing is made of steel. You left it there.
看看针
Look at the needle.
你把罗盘弄坏了，笨蛋
You buggered the compass, you stupid bastard.
- 对不起，我没想到，真的- - - 卡车停下
- Jeez, boss, I wasn't thinking. I'm real... - Stop the bloody truck.
何时放在那的？
So when did you put it there?
我天亮时喝的咖啡
Well, I drank some coffee just at sunrise, boss.
偏离了5小时，40度 你这个笨蛋！
Five hours. Forty degrees off. Stupid bastard.
大班呼叫蓝吉，大班呼叫蓝吉 听到没有？拜托
Big Ben calling Ramjee. Do you read me, for chrissakes?
- 蓝吉，快回答 - 大班，你在哪？
- Ramjee, come in. - Big Ben, where the hell are you?
抱歉，这个白痴把罗盘弄坏了
Look, I'm sorry. This idiot bugged the compass.
我等了三天整，你去哪了？
I've been waiting three bloody days! Where the bloody hell are you?
本来我们早就到了 现在偏离方向了
We could have been there, but we're way off course.
我们要花5小时才能走回原路
Now we have to backtrack for at least five hours to find our bearings.
又回原路了，可能在连络范围外
We're going back in our tracks, so we'll be out of range again.
等进入范围再连络你
I'll contact you when we come back into range.
小奇尔看见土狼足迹
Little Xiri saw hyena tracks.
足迹是刚采的 他知道土狼在附近
The spoor was very fresh so he knew the hyena must be close.
而且是下风，它一定会闻到
And it was downwind, so it was sure to smell him.
他想父亲的话...
He remembered his father had said:
"只要你个头比它大，它就会离开"
"If you're taller than the hyena, it will keep its distance."
土狼不明白这个傢伙 怎么突然变高了
It couldn't understand how this small creature had grown tall so suddenly.
或许土狼希望奇尔再变小 所以就跟著来了
Perhaps the hyena hoped that Xiri would get small again, so it followed...
但保持著适当的距离
... at a respectful distance.
我们的飞机被吹来这...
Well, we got flown here in a kind of a plane...
然后我就找不到马歇尔博士了
...and then I kind of lost Dr. Marshall.
上吉普车，快！
Get in the jeep. Move.
在那等
Wait there.
- 好，袋子留著 - 为什么？
- Okay, but leave your bag. - Why?
- 你会打人 - 不会，我保证不会
- You swat people. - No, I won't. I promise.
- 我把石头拿出来 - 你把石头放在里面？
- Look, I'll take out the rocks. - You got rocks in there?
你开车
You drive.
上车
In there.
发动
Start her up.
往那走
That way.
奇哥看见另一个外人的足迹...
Xixo saw another track made by a heavy person...
由脚印判断是一个情况不好的人
... and the footprints told of a man who was in a bad way.
他对脚印说：
He spoke to the track:
"我知道你需要帮忙 不过我得先找孩子"
"I can see you need help but I must find my children."
向右转
Turn right.
停
Stop.
嘿，是我的吉普
Hey, that's my jeep.
我知道，早知道了
I know, I knew it.
- 去吸油 - 汽油？
- Go siphon. - Gas?
但我的油箱是空的
But my tank was almost empty.
要命！
Oh, boy.
嗨！
Hi.
奇哥说："我不知该怎么办
Xixo said, "I don't know what to do.
你需要有人找水给你 不过我担心自己的孩子
You need someone to find water for you, but I'm worried about my children.
我走了两天两夜 还没找到呢
I've been running for two days, and I haven't found them.
我想他们可能在很远"
I think they're very far."
有多少？
What have you got?
大约两公升
About two liters.
14，15公里
Fourteen, 15 kilometers.
- 里面还有多少？ - 还可跑20公里
- How much have you got in here? - 20 kilometers.
- 你基地多远？ - 60，65公里
- And how far is your base? - Sixty, 65.
老天
Oh, my God.
- 我的基地才20公里 - 闭嘴！
- My base is only 20 kilometers. - Shut up.
上车
Get up.
小心！
Watch it!
住手！
Stop it!
叫你住手
I said, stop it!
马上住手
Stop it right now!
小姐，这玩意得小心
Lady, be careful with that thing.
- 给我吧 - 我不要
- Give it to me. - I won't.
我是好人呀 他是臭古巴佬
But I'm the good guy here. He's a bloody Cuban.
给我吧！
Give it to me.
小姐
Jeez, lady.
没错，我要发威
Yes, make my day.
好吧，小姐 我基地只有20公里
Okay, se駉rita. My base is only 20 kilometers away.
明天有班机去古巴
There gonna be a plane to Cuba tomorrow.
- 我送你去 - 这小子不知道这是哪儿
- I'll take you there. - This guy doesn't know where he is.
- 你如何找基地？ - 你找的到，你很聪明
- How are you going to find your base? - You can find it. You're so smart.
- 去我的基地 - 谁说的？
- We're going to my base. - Who says?
- 我说的 - 住口！
- I says! - Stop it!
你，给我上车
You, get behind the wheel.
不
No.
不行，退回去 你们得在一起
No, get back. You gotta stay together.
牵他的手
Take his hand.
我叫你牵手
I said hold hands!
好了，过来
Okay, get in.
你绕过那边
You go around that way.
好的
Okay.
- 现在你们谁能开飞机？ - 我能！
- Now, can either of you fly a plane? - Yeah, I can.
好，开回原来的地方
Good. Drive back to where we started.
小心！老板
Watch it, boss!
糟了，老板，压死一个小孩
Jeez, boss, we killed a little kid.
- 坐下，我们得离开 - 但老板，他是个小孩子呀！
- Sit down. We've got to get out of here. - But, boss, it was a little kid.
他没事
He's okay.
- 老板，还有一个 - 王八蛋
- Jeez, there's another one. - Bugger.
奇尔！奇尔！
Xiri! Xiri!
奇沙不知该去哪
Now Xisa didn't know which way to go.
万一弟弟一个人被留在后面呢？
What if her little brother had been left back there?
停车
Stop here.
土人在这儿找到我的
This is where the Bushman found me.
这表示飞机一定....
That means the plane must be...
这小子扫把星
That guy's only bad news.
- 跟他去 - 汽油不够了
- Follow him. - We're low on gas.
- 跟他去 - 汽油不够
- Follow him. - We low on gas.
跟去
Follow him.
嗨！
Hi.
手握起来！
Hold hands.
从那边下车
Get out that side.
去那边
Go that way.
停！
Stop.
再见，谢谢
Goodbye, thank you.
怎么了？
What happened?
没事！只是脱水罢了
It's nothing, just kind of dehydrated.
- W代表水吗？ - 我不必告诉你
- Does W stand for water? - I don't have to tell you.
嘴张开
Okay, open your mouth.
把我埋在这的人是谁？
Who's the little guy who gave me that stuff?
不知道，他神出鬼没的
I don't know. He just keeps on appearing and disappearing.
- 他们是谁？ - 是士兵
- Who are they? - They're soldiers.
他们看起来很亲密
They look very affectionate.
不对！
No.
- 是你的囚犯？ - 差不多
- Are they your prisoners? - Kind of.
是人质，她抢了我的吉普 又绑架我们
We're hostages. She hijacked my jeep and she kidnapped us.
是你先动武的！你们俩 他有，他也有
You did it to me first! Both of them. He did it and then he did it.
- 她先打我的 - 你打他？
- She hit me first. - You hit him?
- 对 - 她也打我，差点要我命
- Yeah. - She hit me too. Damn near killed me.
你打了他们？
You hit them?
- 用枪劫持他们？ - 对
- Took them prisoner with a gun? - Yeah.
我们还是在走回头路
No, we're still backtracking.
- 继续走 - 老板
- Keep going. - Yes, boss.
差点又压死一个土人
We nearly knocked over another crazy Bushman.
- 你还在蛮荒国度？ - 哪儿来的都不知道
- You still in Bushmen country? - It beats me where they come from.
- 你说不会有人看见你的 - 土人不算
- You said nobody would see you. - Bushmen don't count.
- 老天 - 班，怎么回事？
- Oh, my God. - Ben, what happened?
- 土人爬到车上 - 什么意思？
- Bloody Bushman was crawling all over. - What do you mean?
你干什么？还好吧？ 还好吧？
What are you doing? Hey, you okay? What are you doing?
你干什么？
What are you doing?
在上面干什么？
What were you doing up there?
- 你有没有看见象牙？ - 不知道，他一定有
- Did he see the ivory? - I don't know. He must have.
- 不能放他走 - 没错
- Then you can't let him go. - That's right.
你是监猎员
You a game warden?
抓上来
Get him in here.
你上车跟我们来，上车
You come with us. You get in there.
拿去
Here.
- 老板？ - 逼他上车
- Boss? - Make him get in.
上车跟我们走，你上车
You come with us. You get in there.
你上车！
You get in there!
不能这么做，上车
You mustn't do that. Get in there.
你什么都做不好
Can't you do anything right?
- 老板 - 把他绑起来
- Jeez, boss. - Get me a tie-down.
你打算怎么做，老板？
What are you gonna do, boss?
这么做是非法的又怎样 是他们先的
So what if it's illegal, they did it to me.
他要走那边 他要走那边
He wants to go that way, he wants to go that way.
有枪的人可以决定
The one with the gun gets to say.
我有枪所以决定去飞机那
And I've got the gun, and I say we go to the plane.
好的
Okay.
上吉普
In the jeep.
我们一到飞机那，吉普就还你
When we get there, you can have your jeep back.
- 还有枪 - 再说吧！
- And my gun. - We'll see about that.
- 你这是干什么？ - 是他的东西
- What do you think you're doing? - It's his, boss.
停！
Stop.
印子又出现了
Here are those tracks again.
飞机一定在那边
The plane must be that way.
- 我不想再当轮子了 - 我们可以修
- I'm not gonna be the wheel again. - Now we can fix it.
- 我没看到唧筒 - 不要，看好他们
- I don't see a pump. - Don't! You've got to watch them.
- 是你的人？ - 不是
- One of yours? - No.
监猎员
Game rangers.
- 你打算怎么做？ - 别让他看见象牙
- What are we gonna do? - Don't let him see the ivory.
或许他们有唧筒
Maybe they've got a pump.
你能借我们唧筒吗？
Could you lend us a pump?
什么？
What?
我们能借唧筒用在...？
Could we borrow a pump with a...?
噢，不要！
Oh, no!
你们对他怎样了？
What have you done to him?
丢掉！
Drop that!
Throw it away!
乔治
George.
拿枪
Get the gun.
现在怎么办，老板？
What do we do now, boss?
- 绑起来 - 老板？
- Tie them up. - Boss?
拿过来
Give me that.
- 拿绳子 - 是，老板
- Get the tie-downs. - Yes, boss.
- 怎么回事？ - 我讨厌盗猎的
- What's this about? - I don't like game rangers.
- 我不是盗猎的 - 我也不是
- I'm not a game ranger. - Me too.
- 我只是找到这个，老板 - 两个两个绑
- This is all I've got, boss. - Tie them two by two.
这下该怎么做？
What are we gonna do now, boss?
我得跟蓝吉谈谈
I gotta talk to Ramjee.
大班呼叫蓝吉，听到没有？
Big Ben calling Ramjee. Do you read me?
蓝吉，听到没有？
Ramjee, do you read me?
距离太远了
Out of range again.
乔治，你看到圆顶了吗？
George, you see that dome?
我上去连络
I'm gonna go up there to get range.
去告诉蓝吉
Got to talk to Ramjee about this.
交给你了，好好看著他们
I'm leaving you in charge. You watch these people.
你们没事吧？乖一点 不会伤到你们
Okay, now, you people. You behave, nobody gets hurt.
拿枪！
Get the gun!
嘿，你不能这么做 老板会杀了你
Hey, you mustn't do that. My boss will kill you!
- 拿到了 - 好，走吧
- Got it. - Okay, let's go.
- 上车 - 什么意思？
- Get in. - What do you mean, "Get in"?
快走
Move it.
先生，一起来吧
Mister, come with us.
- 我也要去，他会杀我的 - 你，一档上路
- I'm gonna come too. He's gonna kill me. - You, give me first gear.
快！
Hurry.
- 我早说没汽油的 - 我们下车
- I told you we're low on gas. - Let's get out of here.
快走
Move your ass, man.
今天真精彩，盗猎的 士兵和女人
What a day. Game rangers, two soldiers and a woman.
- 你怎么对他们的？ - 把他们绑起来
- What did you do with them? - I tied them up.
怎么回事？
What the hell?
乔治！
George!
是的，老板？
Yes, boss?
该你了！
Your turn!
- 该你了！ - 不，不是！
- Your turn! - No, it's not!
- 是！ - 不，不是！
- It is! - No, it's not!
非逮到这混蛋
I'll get the bastard!
起来帮我松绑
No, get up. Untie me.
快呀
Come on.
嘿！
Hey!
天啊
Oh, man.
等一下 他没那么疯
Wait a minute. He's not so crazy.
他知道自己在做什么
He knows what he's doing.
他放火烧出一条生路
He's making a firebreak. Clever little bugger.
会烧完的
It'll burn out now.
烧完了
That's it.
是你的孩子？
They're your kids?
我们刚才碰过面 有一个小的还有另一个
We passed them back there. There's a tiny one and the other one.
对，那边
That way.
- 你怎么哭了？ - 他的孩子不见了
- Why are you crying? - He lost his kids.
我告诉他在哪
I told him where to find them.
你又要走了
So you have to disappear again.
再见...
Goodbye...
谢谢你
...and thank you.
再见，谢谢你
Goodbye and thank you.
小心！他有枪
Watch it! He's got a gun!
回来呀！
Out of my way!
- 我要你们再做一次 - 做什么？！
- I want you guys to do that again. - Do what?!
- 刚才做的 - 为什么？
- What you just did. - What the hell for?
是远距离 他打不中移动的目标的
It's a telescopic sight. He can't hit a moving target.
- 不！ - 当我一下令...
- No! - When I say go...
你就拼命跑，好吗？
...you run around like crazy. All right?
开始！
Go!
别动啊，混蛋
Stand still, you bastards.
丢掉
Throw it away.
好的，好的... 我是你的囚犯
Okay. Okay. Okay. I'm your goddamn prisoner.
我不要你 没用的人犯
I don't want you. You're a shitty prisoner.
奇尔！
Xiri!
不要一次拉拉杂杂说一堆 告诉我你在哪里就好了
你说什么？
- 好了，谢谢 - 好的，再见
- Okay, thank you. - Okay, goodbye.
一路回古巴，可别迷路了
Bugger off to Cuba and don't get lost.
看到那个山丘了吗？
See that hill over there?
直走过去，就找到吉普了
You head straight for it, and you'll find your jeep.
再见！
Goodbye.
好，出来
Okay, out.
你开车
You drive the jeep.
- 上哪去？老板 - 去我基地
- Where we going, boss? - To my base.
我们会判多久？
How long will we get?
你可能一年 但这个混蛋可久了
Maybe you'll get a year, but this bastard's gonna sit for a long time.
ECACL会议
There are 12 planes and 9 helicopters searching...
他们一共派出12架飞机 9架直升机...
搜索4百公里范围
...in a radius of 400 kilometers.
加起来总共是2万...
So we are covering an area of 20,000...
- 我们现在是不是要接吻呢？ - 是的
- Isn't this where we kiss? - Yes.
拉我上来！上来！
Pull me up! Pull me up!
你撕破我的洋装了，放我下来
You're tearing my dress! Let me down.
放我下来！
No, pull me up.
算了
Don't bother.
我看不见！
I can't see!
老天！
Oh, boy.
现在会做了吧？
Now can you do it right?